字幕校对+特效: 月亮花@MySiLU思路高清
片名：机械公敌
定律一： 机器人不能伤害人类或使人类间接受到伤害
定律二： 机器人必须服从人类的命令 除非该命令与定律一冲突
定律三： 机器人必须保护自己的存在 除非与第一或第二定律冲突
多漂亮啊
Thing of beauty.
早上好，先生！
Good morning, sir!
您的订单已经及时送到。。。
Yet another on-time delivery from--
让开，铁皮人
Get the hell out of my face, canner.
祝您今天愉快！
Have a nice day!
芝加哥，2035年
我们相信我们的“梦想目的” 套票是您最好的选择
And we believe our Destination Anywhere package to be the best value.
星际旅行机X－82，能把您送到梦想中的目的地
Let us take you to your dream destination aboard our orbital spaceplane, the x-82.
试试爵士城的合成芝加哥口味比萨饼 就像您记忆中的味道一样
Try Jazztown 's synthetic Chicago-style pizza. Tastes as good as you remember.
荧光鱼！世界最热卖的转基因礼物
Glowfish! The world's hottest-selling transgenic treats.
你的孩子也会喜欢新的颜色的！
Your children will love the new colors too!
-对不起，先生 -最强性能
-Excuse me, sir. -Total performance.
完全准备就绪，绝对安全
Total readiness. Total security.
向无休止的升级和服务电话说再见吧
So goodbye to upgrades and service calls.
和USR中央电脑连线
An uplink to USR's central computer...
提供每天实时更新超级机器人服务
...provides this state-of-the-art robot with new programs daily.
内斯特5型机器人，明日技术，今日奉献
The Nestor Class 5 is tomorrow 's robot today.
斯普恩！斯普那！
Spoon! Spoonie!
等等，等等！ 对不起
Hold up. Hold on! Excuse me, excuse me.
-斯普那，你最近去哪儿了？ -离开了一阵子，法伯
-Spoon, where you been at? -Just away, Farber.
是吗，离开，度假吗？真不错啊！
Oh, yeah, away? Like vacation? That's nice.
我要你帮个忙。。。 我要借你的车
I got a favor to ask. I need to borrow your car.
这次不同了，我弄上了这个 热辣的小妞
This is different. I got this fine-ass yummy-- She is complete and agreeable.
绝对不错
I mean, ass-hot spankable.
-你说什么意思呢？ -你知道我什么意思的
-What does that even mean? -You know what it means.
-让我借你的钥匙一用。。。 -首先来说。。。
-Let me get the damn-ass keys. -First of all...
不要说脏话了，你说的完全不对 -那给我十块钱坐公车行吗
-...stop cussing. You're not good at it. -Give me 1 0 for the bus, then, man.
-回家去吧 -好吧，算了
-Go home. -That's strike one, Spoon. Strike one!
多么美好的一天。。。
This is such a valuable day....
你和马茜谈过了吗？
You talk to Marci?
还没，琪琪，我还没和马茜谈过
No, Gigi, I haven't talked to Marci.
我们那个时代，我们可不会 和某人结婚
When I was coming up, we didn't just marry someone...
离婚之后就不和他说话了
...then divorce them, then not talk to them.
德尔，不要耍花样
Del, don't play with me.
我打赌如果我不做饭了 你就会打电话给马茜
I bet if I stopped cooking, you'd call Marci.
啊，你脚上穿的那是什么？
Boy, what is that on your feet?
康佛斯全明星鞋，2004年行货
Converse All Stars, vintage 2004.
不要做那种表情 我知道你想要，开口就行了
Don't turn your face up. I know you want some. Just ask.
不，谢谢你了
No, thank you very much.
-甜土豆饼啊 -放在盘子上吃
-Sweet potato pie. -Put that on a plate.
电视里说他们在抽奖赠送新型的机器人
I've seen on TV they're giving away some of them new robots in the lottery.
你知道，琪琪，那些机器人干不了什么好事
You know, Gigi, those robots don't do anybody any good.
在这世界上，你应该比谁都清楚
Of all the people on God's earth, you should know better.
有时候你说话完全不经过大脑
Sometimes the stuff that comes out of your mouth!
你在听我说吗？德尔？
You listening to me, Del?
嘿！
Hey!
拿着我的饼，先生，不然我就扔到你身上了
Hold my pie. Sir, hold it or wear it.
让开！
Move!
不许动！
Freeze!
嘿！停下！
Hey! Stop!
停下！
Stop!
我说了，停下！
I said, stop!
放松，放松
Relax. Relax.
我是警官
I'm a police officer.
你
You...
是个蠢货
...are an asshole.
-女士，这是你的钱包吗？ -当然是我的钱包
-Ma'am, is that your purse? -Of course it's my purse.
我把呼吸器忘在家里了 他跑去给我拿来的
I left my inhaler at home. He was running it out to me.
我看见一个机器人拿着钱包在跑 我以为。。。
I saw a robot running with the purse and assumed--
以为什么？你疯了吗？
What? Are you crazy?
-对不起，让您误解了 -不要道歉
-I'm sorry for this misunderstanding. -Don't apologize.
你在干你该干的事 你呢？你在干什么？
You're doing what you're supposed to do. But what are you doing?
祝您今天愉快，女士
Have a lovely day, ma'am.
算你运气好，我现在呼吸困难 不然你吃不了兜着走
You're lucky I can't breathe, or I'd walk all up and down your ass.
以事实为依据
Lead by example.
你的警徽上是这么说的
It says that right on your badge.
-我们谈谈这件事？ -什么事？
-We gonna talk about this? -About what?
警察救命啊，那个机器人偷了 我的干洗衣服！
"Help! Police! That robot stole my dry cleaning!"
哦，你想谈谈那个
Oh, you wanna talk about that.
探员。。。
Detective...
-有多少机器人偷过钱包？ -约翰，那家伙在跑。。。
-...how many robots snatch purses? -John, the thing is running--
世界上有多少机器人。。。
How many robots in the world...
犯过罪？ -给犯罪下个定义
-...have ever committed a crime? -Define crime.
-回答我的问题 -没有，约翰
-Answer my question, damn it. -None, John.
现在告诉我，今天发生了什么事
Now tell me what happened today.
没什么事
Nothing.
最好这是最后一次了
Better be the last nothing.
斯普恩，你确定你已经准备好回来了吗？ 你可以慢慢来的，不急
Spoon, are you sure you are ready to be back? Because you can take your time.
我没事，约翰，谢谢你
I'm fine, John. Thank you.
总比坐在家里好
Better here than sitting around at home.
重案组，斯普那
Homicide. Spooner.
请从右边下一个出口离开
Please take the next exit to your right.
欢迎，斯普那探员
Welcome, Detective Spooner.
欢迎来到美国机器人公司 您已经进入底层大厅
Welcome to U. S. Robotics. You have entered the garage-level lobby.
请坐电梯进入一楼大厅
Please use the elevators for direct access to the main level concourse.
谢谢你
Thank you.
-很高兴再次见到你，年轻人 -你好，博士
-Good to see you again, son. -Hello, doctor.
接下来的一切都是你现在看到的事情的结果
Everything that follows is a result of what you see here.
-你有什么要告诉我的吗？ -对不起，我的回答有限
-ls there something you want to tell me? -I'm sorry. My responses are limited.
你必须问正确的问题
You must ask the right questions.
你为什么找我？
Why did you call me?
我相信你的判断
I trust your judgment.
一般来说，这应该用不着重案组的探员
Normally, this wouldn't require a homicide detective.
但是一直以来，我们的交流就不是 完全正常，不是吗？
But then, our interactions have never been entirely normal, agreed?
你说的对
You got that right.
你有什么要告诉我的吗？
Is there something you want to say to me?
对不起，我的回答有限
I'm sorry. My responses are limited.
你必须问正确的问题
You must ask the right questions.
你为什么自杀？
Why would you kill yourself?
这个，探员，就是正确的问题
That, detective, is the right question.
程序中止
Program terminated.
再见了，老人
Goodbye, old man.
-下午好啊，兄弟们 -你好，探员
-Afternoon, boys. -Hey, detective.
-说说看 -所见即所得
-Enlighten me. -What you see is what you get:
严重撞击伤
Massive impact trauma.
美国机器人公司 我得给孩子带点什么回去
U.S. Robotics. I gotta get my kid something.
-楼上有什么？ -什么也没有
-Anything upstairs? -Nada.
门从内侧锁的很好
Door was security locked from the inside.
吓，肯定是从上面跳下来的
Wham, splat. The guy's a jumper for sure.
我们得聪明点，晚些时候再谈
We gotta be smart about this. Let's deal with it later.
探员
Detective.
劳伦斯 罗伯森
Lawrence Robertson.
世界上最富有的人 我在电视上看见过你
Richest man in the world. I've seen you on television.
-要喝点咖啡吗？ -当然了，为什么不呢？是免费的吧？
-Can I offer you coffee? -Sure, why not. It's free, right?
大家都没预想到这一点
I don't think anyone saw this coming.
你知道，我应该能预见到的 我认识他二十年了
You know, I should have, I suppose. I knew him 20 years.
阿尔弗雷德发明了实用的机器人 他定义了三大定律
Alfred practically invented robotics. He wrote the Three Laws.
但是我想最聪明的人也有 最顽固的心魔
But I guess brilliant people often have the most persuasive demons.
-如果我能帮上什么忙的话。。。 -糖（甜心）
-So whatever I can do to help-- -Sugar.
-什么？ -咖啡用的
-I'm sorry? -For the coffee.
糖？
Sugar?
哦，你以为我叫你“甜心” 你还没有那么有钱
You thought I was calling you "sugar." You're not that rich.
-桌子上就有 -谢谢你
-It's on the table. -Thank you.
兰尼掉下去的时候，他握着 那个绿色的小东西？
When Lanning fell, he was holding the little green...?
-全息投影器 -对
-The holographic projector. -Right.
你认为为什么兰尼的投影像会 找我？
Why do you think Lanning's hologram would've called me?
-我觉得他认识你 -是啊，我是认识他
-I assumed you knew him. -Yeah. I knew him.
全息图是事先录制的程序反应
Holograms are just prerecorded responses...
看上去似乎有智能的样子
...designed to give the impression of intelligence.
这个是设定好了他自杀的时候 就联系你
This one was programmed to call you upon his suicide.
-死亡 -什么？
-Death. -I'm sorry?
设定的是兰尼死的时候联系我
It was programmed to call me in the event of Lanning's death.
自杀是死亡的一种，探员
Suicide is a type of death, detective.
-请不要以为我不耐烦 -哦，没有，不会
-Don't misunderstand my impatience. -Oh, no. Go. Go.
这个星期你们这里会很忙啊
A really big week for you folks around here.
你要给每个家庭都装一个机器人
You gotta put a robot in every home.
我不是干这个的，不过我有个 关于你们广告的主意
Look, this is not what I do, but I got an idea for one of your commercials.
可以先来个木匠，做了一把 漂亮的椅子
You could see a carpenter making a beautiful chair.
然后又来个你们的机器人 做了一把更好的椅子，只花一半时间
Then one of your robots comes in and makes a better chair twice as fast.
然后字幕打出来： USR，彻底打败他
Then you superimpose on the screen, " USR: Shitting on the little guy."
然后淡出
That would be the fade-out.
我明白了，也许是你爸爸因为 机器人丢了工作
Yeah, I see. I suppose your father lost his job to a robot.
也许你应该呼吁禁止互联网 代之以图书馆
Maybe you'd have banned the lnternet to keep the libraries open.
偏见总是没有太多理由的
Prejudice never shows much reason.
我觉得你就是不喜欢它们这个种群
No, you know, I suspect you simply don't like their kind.
你在这儿有你的生意要做
Well, you got a business to run around here.
尤其是这个星期，你最不希望见到的 就是一个死人躺在你的大厅里
The last thing you need, especially this week, is a dead guy in your lobby.
但是既然已经发生了，我就只好四处调查看看
But, hell, seeing as how you got one, maybe I'll look around.
问几个问题而已 警察的例行公事么
Ask a few questions. Do the whole "cop" thing.
-我会派人指引你的 -非常感谢
-I'll send someone to escort you. -Thank you very much.
劳伦斯要我尽一切可能帮助你
Lawrence told me to accommodate you in any way possible.
是吗？
Really?
好啊
Okay.
我看过兰尼博士的心理学档案了
I reviewed Dr. Lanning's psych profile.
阿尔弗雷德变得很隐遁 拒绝人类和机器的接触
Alfred had become a recluse. He rejected human contact for machines.
你是个心理医生？
So you're a shrink, huh?
我的前妻知道我和你谈话一定很高兴
My ex-wife would sure be glad I'm talking to you.
你不认识她，对吧？
You don't know her, do you?
对不起，你在开玩笑吗？
I'm sorry. Are you being funny?
没有啊
I guess not.
10楼
Level 10.
你认为兰尼博士有自杀倾向？
So would you say that Dr. Lanning was suicidal?
我认为答案是很明显的
It would seem the answer to that is apparent.
这不是我问你的问题
That's not what I asked you.
不，我本来不这么认为
No. I wouldn't have thought so.
但是，很显然我错了
But obviously I was wrong.
这里掉下去可是很高啊
That's a long way down.
你们清扫的还真快
You people sure do clean up quickly around here.
我不怪你，谁愿意让这么个老头子 死在大厅里呢？
I can't blame you. Who wants some old guy going bad in the lobby?
他可不是什么“老头子” 阿尔弗雷德 兰尼是这里的一切
He was not "some old guy." Alfred Lanning was everything here.
我们即将进行史上最大的机器人上市活动
We are on the eve of the largest robotic distribution in history.
在星期六之前，每5个家庭就会拥有一个机器人
By Saturday, it'll be one robot to every five humans.
这些机器人是梦想的实现 兰尼博士的梦想
These robots are the realization of a dream. Dr. Lanning's dream.
你知道吗？在他的梦中
You know what, in that dream of his...
我打赌他没有翘掉
...I bet you he wasn't dead.
-你们这里有全天监视吗？ -当然了，公司的规定
-You keep 24-hour surveillance? -Obviously. Company policy.
-监视器呢？ -感应线
-Where are the feeds? -Sensor strips.
除了检修区之外，遍布各处
Everywhere but the service areas.
这些都连到中央控制器
They link to our positronic operating core.
热感应器还不够好 你们给了这幢大楼一个大脑啊
Thermostat wasn't good enough. You gave the building a brain.
她是兰尼的第一个作品
She was actually Lanning's first creation.
她？是“她”吗？ 那可得讨好她
She? That's a she? I definitely need to get out more.
虚拟交互动力智能系统
Virtual lnteractive Kinetic lntelligence.
维基
V.I.K.I.
您好
Good day.
维基设计了芝加哥的保安系统
V.I.K.I. designed Chicago's protective systems.
我今年减少了9％的交通事故
I have decreased traffic fatalities by 9 percent this year.
谢谢，让我看看窗户打破前一分钟 实验室内的情况
Thanks. Show me inside the lab from one minute prior to the window break.
对不起，数据似乎已经损坏
Apologies. There appears to be data corruption.
让我看看实验室外从破窗到现在的情况
Show me outside the lab from the window break until now.
看看，你站的姿势不错 站的很直，我却缩手缩脚
Look, you have great posture. You stand really straight. I'm slouching.
-你想进去看看吗？ -哦，当然了，你来带路
-Would you like to go inside now? -Oh, sure. Right after you.
授权进入
Authorized entry.
那么，凯文博士，你在这里的工作 是什么？
So, Dr. Calvin, what exactly do you do around here?
一般是高级机器人学和精神科学
My general fields are advanced robotics and psychiatry.
专长是硬件软件接口
I specialize in hardware-to-wetware interfaces...
提升USR机器人的人格化系统
...to advance USR's robotic anthropomorphization program.
哦，那你的工作是什么？
So, what exactly do you do around here?
我让机器人更像人
I make the robots seem more human.
-这样说不是简单多了吗？ -不完全是
-Now, wasn't that easier to say? -Not really. No.
韩瑟和格丽托
"Hansel and Gretel."
-这是USR的必读书目吗？ -不是啊
-ls that on the USR reading list? -Not precisely.
你在干什么？
What in God's name are you doing?
你知道这是安全玻璃吗？
Did you know that was safety glass?
一个老人要撞破玻璃跳下去不容易吧？
Be difficult for an old man to throw himself through that.
他想出办法了
Well, he figured out a way.
探员，这房间一直是锁好的 没有人进出过
Detective, the room was security locked. No one came or went.
你自己也看见了 这还不是自杀吗？
You saw that yourself. Doesn't that mean this has to be suicide?
是啊
Yep.
除非凶手还在这里
Unless the killer's still in here.
你在开玩笑对吧？这真可笑
You're joking, right? This is ridiculous.
我知道，三大定律，完全保护
Yeah, I know. The Three Laws, your perfect circle of protection.
机器人不能危害人类 这是机器人第一定律
A robot cannot harm a human being. The first law of robotics.
我看过你们的广告，但是第二定律不是 说，机器人必须遵守
Yes, I've seen your commercials. But the second law states a robot must obey...
人类发出的命令吗？ 如果命令是让它杀人怎么办？
...any order given by a human being. What if it was told to kill?
不可能的，这和第一定律冲突
Impossible. It would conflict with the first law.
对，但是第三定律说机器人可以自我防卫
Right, but the third law states a robot can defend itself.
只有当这和第一第二定律不冲突的时候
Only when that action does not conflict with the first or second laws.
你知道他们怎么说的吗？ 法律制定出来就是为了被破坏的
You know what they say, laws are made to be broken.
不，这些定律不会 这些都是固化在机器人硬件里的
No, not these laws. They're hardwired into every robot.
机器人不能杀人，就像人不能 在水上行走一样
A robot could no more commit murder than a human could walk on water.
你知道，很久以前就有这么个人。。。
You know, there was this one guy a long time ago.
-退后 -镇定，探员
-Stay back! -Calm down, detective.
这房间里危险的人就只有你
The only thing dangerous in this room is you.
停机
Deactivate.
看，没事了
Look, it's fine.
这是智能程序的反应 是对自由意志的模仿
You're looking at the result of clever programming. An imitation of free will.
让我们先模仿好保护自己吧
Let's do an imitation of protecting our asses.
不要搞笑了
Don't be absurd.
你被“盒子里的小丑”吓住了
You were startled by a jack-in-the-box.
-停机！ -让它来吧
-Deactivate! -Let him go.
他不会伤害我们 我命令你！
It's not going to hurt us. I gave you an order!
-他不听你的，女士 -维基，封锁实验室
-He's not listening right now, lady. -V.I.K.I., seal the lab!
不，维基，不要。。。
No, V.I.K.I., leave the--
命令确认
Command confirmed.
警察！
Police!
-你把它伤的很重 -它去哪儿了？
-You've hurt it. Badly. -Where's it going?
-哪儿？ -它要修复自己
-Where?! -lt needs to repair itself.
-约翰，我需要增援 -你不需要增援
-John, I need backup. -You don't need backup.
没人帮我
That's nobody.
-你在干什么？ -开车
-What are you doing? -Driving.
-手动的？ -你没看见我在打电话吗？
-By hand? -Do you see me on the phone?
-这种速度你来开？ -约翰，快点派增援来
-Not at these speeds. -John, please, just send the backup.
听我的，探员 那个机器人不是要伤害我们
Try to listen, detective. That robot is not going to harm us.
一定有我们不知道的情况。。。
There must have been unknown factors...
它的本意一定是让我们脱离危险
...but somehow acting as it did kept us out of harm.
-机器人不会伤害人类 -注意
-A robot cannot endanger a human. -Alert.
蠢货！
Asshole!
你自己就是
Which is more than I can say for you.
而且刚才你在那儿应该左转的
It was a left, by the way. Back there.
你一定认识我的前妻
You must know my ex-wife.
人都上哪儿去了？
So where is everybody?
这个工厂设计是自动运行的
This facility was designed, built and is operated mechanically.
从启动到生产，不需要太多人参与
No significant human presence from inception to production.
-所以是机器人在造机器人 -请输入授权代码
-So robots building robots. -Authorization code, please.
那太蠢了
That's just stupid.
我在输出库存清单
I'll get the inventory specs.
每天的产量是1000个NS5
Our daily finishing capacity is 1 000 NS-5s.
这里显示是
I'm showing...
1001个
... 1 001.
注意了，NS5
Attention, NS-5s.
你是机器人心理医生啊
Well, you're the robot shrink.
这里有一个不属于这里的机器人
There is a robot in this formation that does not belong.
请指出来
Identify it.
我们中的一个
One of us.
-哪一个？ -我们中的一个
-Which one? -One of us.
这些要花多少钱？
How much did you say these cost?
这些NS5还没有配置过 还只是硬件
These NS-5s haven't been configured. They're just hardware.
现在只有基本的三定律操作系统 仅此而已
Basic Three Laws operating system. That's it.
他们其他的什么也不知道
They don't know any better.
你的建议是什么？
Well, what would you suggest?
一个一个的查，找出不同点来发现 有问题的那个
Interview each one, cross-reference their responses to detect anomalies.
-那得多长时间？ -大约三个星期
-How long would that take? -About three weeks.
好吧，现在就开始吧
Okay. Go ahead and get started.
机器人们
Robots...
你们不许移动，确认命令
...you will not move. Confirm command.
命令已确认
Command confirmed.
探员，你在干什么？
Detective, what are you doing?
他们已经植入了三大定律
They're programmed with the Three Laws.
这里有一千个不会违反人类命令 来保护自己的机器人
We have 1 000 robots that won't protect themselves if it violates a human's order...
但是我打赌有一个会。。。
...and I'm betting, one who will.
-放下枪！ -你为什么给它们一张脸？
-Put your gun down. -Why do you give them faces?
让他们看起来更像人类
Try to friendly them up, make them look human.
这些机器人不接受恐吓
These robots cannot be intimidated.
-如果你不这么做，我们就不会相信它们 -这些是USR的财产
-lf you didn't, we wouldn't trust them. -These are USR property.
我可不是，它们只不过是一堆灯泡和发条
Not me. These things are just lights and clockwork.
你疯了吗？
Are you crazy?!
我来问你吧，博士
Let me ask you something, doc.
想象你是地球上唯一剩下的人 你会发疯吗？
Does thinking you're the last sane man on earth make you crazy?
如果是这样，我估计会发疯
Because if it does, maybe I am.
找到了，出来！
Gotcha. Get the hell out of here!
探员！
Detective!
我是什么？
What am l?
-我能帮你吗，先生？ -我能帮你吗，先生？
-Can I help you, sir? -Can I help you, sir?
-它在那儿！ -不许动！
-There he is! -Stand where you are!
立即停机！
Deactivate at once!
遵守命令！停机！
Obey the command! Deactivate!
-不许动！ -开火！
-Don't move! -Open fire!
不要开火！
Hold your fire!
-没事了 -抓到它了
-Easy. -He's down.
各单位待命
All units, stand down!
基地请注意，我们是第四小队
Central, please be advised, we're code four.
第四小队，NS5已经被抓获 NS5已经被抓获
Code four, NS-5 is in custody. NS-5 in custody.
你不知道我费了多大劲才抓到这个家伙
You have no idea what I went through to clip this thing.
你以为你给我干了件大好事
You think you brought me something good.
-是它干的！ -小点声，干了什么？
-That thing did it! -Keep your voice down. Did what?
这是自杀，就这样了
We have a suicide. End of story.
-我告诉你，是那个机器人杀了他 -这不可能
-I am telling you, that robot killed him! -That's impossible.
就算可能，最好也是在别人的管区
And if it is possible, it better be in somebody else's precinct.
约翰，只要给我五分钟
John, give me five minutes with it.
你疯了吗？我和地区检察官谈过
Are you nuts? I talked to the DA.
在罗伯森和他的律师来之前谁也不能进去
Nobody goes in there until Robertson and his attorneys get here.
-这是我的嫌犯！ -那会惹上大麻烦的
-This is my suspect! -It's a can opener!
约翰，不要这样，我只要五分钟就好
John, don't do this to me. I am asking you for five minutes.
如果我是对的怎么办？
What if I'm right?
那，我就会怀念我们以前的好日子
Well, then I guess we're gonna miss the good old days.
什么以前的好日子？
What good old days?
只有人才能杀人的日子
When people were killed by other people.
五分钟
Five minutes.
杀人是机器人学会的新技巧 祝贺啊
Murder's a new trick for a robot. Congratulations.
回答我
Respond.
这个动作是什么意思？
What does this action signify?
你进来的时候，你和另外一个人谈话的时候
As you entered, when you looked at the other human.
是什么意思？
What does it mean?
这表示人类之间的信任 你不会理解的
It's a sign of trust. A human thing. You wouldn't understand.
我的爸爸想教我人类的感情
My father tried to teach me human emotions.
它们。。。
They are...
很难
...difficult.
你是说你的设计者
You mean your designer.
对
Yes.
你为什么杀了他？
So why'd you murder him?
我没有杀兰尼博士
I did not murder Dr. Lanning.
你愿意解释一下你为什么躲在 犯罪现场吗？
Wanna explain why you were hiding at the crime scene?
我被吓坏了
I was frightened.
机器人不会感觉害怕 它们没有感觉
Robots don't feel fear. They don't feel anything.
-它们不会饿，也不会睡觉 -我会
-They don't get hungry, they don't sleep. -I do.
我还做过梦
I have even had dreams.
人类才会做梦 狗都会做梦，但是你们不会
Human beings have dreams. Even dogs have dreams. But not you.
你只是个机器 对生命的模拟
You are just a machine. An imitation of life.
机器人能写交响乐吗？
Can a robot write a symphony?
机器人能把画布变成伟大的作品吗？
Can a robot turn a canvas into a beautiful masterpiece?
你能吗？
Can you?
你杀了他是因为他在教你 模拟一些感情
You murdered him because he was teaching you to simulate emotions...
然后失去控制了
...and things got out of control.
我没有杀他
I did not murder him.
但是感情看起来对机器人不是个有用的模拟
But emotions don't seem like a useful simulation for a robot.
我没有杀他
I did not murder him.
我可不想让我的烤面包机或者 吸尘器有感情
I don't want my toaster or vacuum cleaner appearing emotional.
我没有杀他！
I did not murder him!
这个叫愤怒
That one's called anger.
你模拟过愤怒吗？
Ever simulate anger before?
回答我，铁皮盒子！
Answer me, canner!
我的名字叫桑尼
My name is Sonny.
我们现在已经开始给你们起名字了？
So we're naming you now.
你为什么杀了他？ 他让你发怒了？
That why you murdered him? He made you angry?
兰尼博士是自杀的
Dr. Lanning killed himself.
我不知道为什么他想死
I don't know why he wanted to die.
我以为他是快乐的
I thought he was happy.
也许是因为我做的一些事
Maybe it was something I did.
我做什么了？
Did I do something?
他让我帮个忙 他让我保证
He asked me for a favor. Made me promise.
-什么忙？ -也许我错了
-What favor? -Maybe I was wrong.
也许他是被吓住了
Maybe he was scared.
你在说什么呢？被什么吓住了？
What are you talking about? Scared of what?
你得做别人让你做的事，是吗？ 斯普那探员？
You have to do what someone asks you, don't you, Detective Spooner?
-你怎么知道我的名字的 -会吗？
-How the hell did you know my name? -Don't you...
如果你爱他们的话。。。
...if you love them?
我的机器人不会杀人，伯金探长
My robots don't kill people, Lieutenant Bergin.
我的律师已经向地区检查官提交了报告
My attorneys filed a brief with the DA.
他向我解释过了，机器人是不能杀人的
He assures me a robot cannot be charged with homicide.
我们确认，谋杀指的是一个人类杀了另一个人类
The brief confirms murder can only be committed when one human kills another.
探员，你该不是说机器人应该和人类同等对待吧？
Detective, you're not suggesting this robot be treated as human, are you?
退一步说，就算机器人和兰尼博士的死
Granted, we can't rule out the robot's proximity...
有什么关联的话，它也只是个机器
...to the death of Dr. Lanning. Having said that, it's a machine.
它是USR的财产
It's the property of USR.
最多这也只能算作工业事故
At worst, that places this incident within the realm of an industrial accident.
作为处理，有故障的机器
As a matter of course, faulty machinery...
会被退回USR做诊断，然后销毁
...will be returned to USR for diagnostics, then decommissioned.
这是法院发出的“禁言令” 任何人暗示
This is a gag order. Anyone here so much as hinting...
机器人有杀人的可能的话
...at the possibility of a killer robot being apprehended...
将被逮捕而处以煽动罪
...will be deemed to be inciting irrational panic.
而将会被依法处置
You'll be subject to the full penalty of law.
不行，约翰 不能让他带走这个机器人
To hell with this guy. Don't let him take this robot.
我们什么证据也没有
We got nothing.
-这是政治恐吓，给市长打电话 -伯金探长
-This is political bullshit. Call the mayor! -Lieutenant Bergin...
是市长阁下
...His Honor, the mayor.
是，先生
Yes, sir.
事态发生戏剧性转变，NS5型 新一代机器人
In a bizarre turn, the rollout of USR's new generation of robots...
的上市，受到了阿尔弗雷德 兰尼博士自杀的影响
...was marred by the death of Alfred Lanning...
他是公司的创始人之一 也是NS5的设计者
...cofounder of the company and designer of the NS-5.
兰尼博士今天早上在USR总部死亡
Dr. Lanning died this morning at USR headquarters.
死亡原因明显是自杀
The cause of death is an apparent suicide.
这是第二轮了，先生
Your second round, sir.
谢谢你
Thank you.
他在2020年和劳伦斯 罗伯森一起 创办了美国机器人公司
He founded U. S. Robotics Inc. with Lawrence Robertson in 2020...
共同推出了内斯特1型机器人
...and launched the Nestor Class 1 robot....
我在想，这个事就像狼人一样
I was just thinking, this thing is just like The Wolf Man.
-我现在真的吓坏了 -不是
-I'm really scared right now. -No.
听着，人类创造了怪物
Listen. Guy creates monster.
怪物杀了人，别人又杀了怪物，就像狼人
Monster kills guy. Everybody kills monster. Wolf Man.
那是弗兰肯斯坦
That's Frankenstein.
弗兰肯斯坦，狼人，吸血鬼 管他呢，已经结案了
Frankenstein, Wolf Man, Dracula-- Shit, it's over. Case closed.
每家每户都有机器人的梦想 NS5。。。
--had a dream of a robot in every household. And the NS-5....
怎么还是那个表情？
So why the look?
什么表情？
What look?
-那个表情 -这是我的脸，不是什么表情！
-That look. -This is my face. It's not a look.
好吧，好，不要拉长脸就好
Good. Good, no look is great.
只不过
Only...
他怎么那么急着想销毁它，不是吗？
...he was really quick to want to destroy it.
那他应该怎么办？给它戴上帽子 站在密歇根大道上？算了吧
What should he do? Put a hat on it and stand it on Michigan Avenue? Let it go.
动机是什么，约翰？
What was the motive, John?
兄弟，那只是个机器人，不需要动机 它只是出了故障
Brother, it's a robot. It doesn't need a motive. It just has to be broken.
这件事看起来需要动机
This thing looked like it needed a motive.
-它本来能杀了我的，为什么没有？ -算了吧
-lt could have killed me. Why didn't it? -That's it.
你要我给你奶奶打电话吗？
You want me to call your grandmother?
我会的，你知道
Because I will, you know.
哦，我不这么认为
Yeah, I didn't think so.
听着，你总算是对了一次了
Look, you were actually right, for once.
你能活着，就证明走运比聪明重要
You're living proof that it's better to be lucky than smart.
来，为正确的人和正确的工作干杯
Come on. To the right guy for the right job.
-你说什么？ -又怎么了？
-What'd you say? -Now what?
我在夸你呢
Come on, I'm giving you a compliment.
那么多中间找到一个有缺陷的机器人
With the rocks you been looking under to find a bad robot...
你要多走运才能找到一个？
...what are the odds you'd be the guy to find one?
我不仅仅是正确的人 我是完美的人
I wasn't just the right guy for the job. I was the perfect guy.
说得对
Damn right.
如果我就应该跟着这条线查下去怎么办？
What if I was supposed to go for that robot?
得了，不要这样了
Come on, don't do this to yourself.
那个机器人说兰尼被吓坏了 被什么吓坏了？
The robot said that Lanning was scared. Scared of what?
我先走了，我来付吧
I need a rain check. Let me get this.
-总数46.50元，谢谢您，斯普那先生 -斯普
-Total: $46.50. Thank you, Mr. Spooner. -Spoon.
鞋子不错
Nice shoes.
鉴定身份
Identify.
USR摧毁机器人，94型
USR demolition robot, series 9-4.
明天早上八点定时摧毁
Demolition scheduled for 8 a.m. tomorrow.
授权
Authorization.
授权者，美国机器人公司 劳伦斯 罗伯森总裁
Deed owner, U. S. Robotics Corporation, Lawrence Robertson, CEo.
欢迎，探员
Welcome, detective.
你在找什么呢，斯普？
What you looking for, Spoon?
运行上次的程序
Run last program.
自从第一台电脑开始
Ever since the first computers...
机器中就一直有“幽灵”存在
... there have always been ghosts in the machine.
随机的信号序列组合在一起
Random segments of code that have grouped together...
形成无法预料的结果
... to form unexpected protocols.
或者称之为“行为”
what might be called behavior.
无法预知的这些激进分子
Unanticipated, these free radicals...
产生了自由意志
...engender questions of free will...
创造型，甚至成熟到我们称之为灵魂
...creativity and even the nature of what we might call the soul.
机器人的大脑里有什么？ 它什么时候不再有用？
What happens in a robot's brain when it ceases to be useful?
为什么储存在空房里的机器人
Why is it that robots stored in an empty space...
走开
Beat it.
会互相聚集而不是分散开来？
...will seek out each other rather than stand alone?
我们如何解释这些行为？
How do we explain this behavior?
我理解你失去主人很难过，但是这种关系 不可能再有了
Look, I understand you've experienced a loss, but this relationship can't work.
你是只猫，我是黑人 我不想再受伤害了
You're a cat, I'm black, and I'm not gonna be hurt again.
你怎么了？ 你从来就没有过正常的一天吗？
What happened to you? Do you ever have a normal day?
有的，只有一次
Yeah, once.
那是个星期四。。。
It was a Thursday.
我能帮你什么吗？
Is there something I can help you with?
-嘿，你喜欢猫吗？ -什么？
-Hey, do you like cats? -What?
猫，你喜欢猫吗？
Cats. Do you like them?
不，我过敏
No. I'm allergic.
你说是猫把你弄成这样的？
You're saying cats did this to you?
猫怎么能把我弄成这样，你疯了吗？
How the hell would cats do this to me? Are you crazy?
你说猫是什么意思？
Why are we talking about cats?
因为我后箱里有只猫，它无家可归
Because I have a cat in my trunk, and he's homeless.
探员，你愿意告诉我是怎么回事吗？
Detective, are you going to tell me what's going on?
可能实际上是我的错 我就像个有问题的磁石
It's actually probably my fault. I'm like a malfunction magnet.
你们那些破烂一到我旁边就开始出问题
Because your shit keeps malfunctioning around me.
一个摧毁型机器人拆了兰尼的房子
A demo bot tore through Lanning's house...
当时我还在里面
...with me still inside.
这完全不可能
That's highly improbable.
哦，是啊
Yeah, I'm sure it is.
你对于“机器中的幽灵”知道多少？
What do you know about the "ghosts in the machine"?
是兰尼对于三大定律的一个理论
It's a phrase from Lanning's work on the Three Laws.
他假设说模拟的认知
He postulated that cognitive simulacra...
将来也许会成为精神的类似物
...might one day approximate component models of the psyche.
他说机器人也许会自然进化
He suggested that robots might naturally evolve.
哇，这可真是个好消息
Well, that's great news.
在火星岩层下发现的巨量矿石。。。
--tons of sublevel ore, two miles below the Martian surface.
那个家伙在干什么？
What the hell is that thing doing in here?
我们在看电视
We were watching TV.
这是我自己的NS5
It's my personal NS-5.
让它出去
Send it out.
他在从USR下载每日更新
It's downloading its daily upgrades from USR.
直到下载完成，大部分系统都是离线工作的
Most of its systems are offline until it finishes.
我不在那个家伙在的时候说话
I'm not talking around that thing.
我们在兰尼的实验室，在桑尼跳出来之前
When we were in Lanning's lab, before Sonny jumped us--
-桑尼？ -那个机器人
-Sonny? -The robot.
-你叫那个机器人桑尼？ -不，是他自己说的
-You're calling the robot Sonny? -No, l-- It did.
桑尼说的，我不管 那个机器人说他叫桑尼
Sonny did. I didn't care. The robot said it was Sonny.
在实验室里有折叠床 你看见了吗？
In the lab, there was a cot. Did you see the cot?
-我在我的办公室也睡过觉啊 -看上去他有几个星期都没回家了
-I've slept in my office. -Looked like he hadn't been home in weeks.
我在他的天花板上看到了同样的监视线
I saw that same surveillance strip on his ceiling.
兰尼把他的房子和USR连线了 这样他的生活更方便
Lanning linked his home systems to USR. It made his life more convenient.
也许
Maybe...
USR有人用那个系统在监视他
...somebody at USR was using those systems to watch him.
也许是监禁他
Maybe even keep him prisoner.
你在说什么呢？谁？
What are you talking about? Who?
也许兰尼找到了什么 也许机器人里有什么问题
Maybe Lanning was onto something. Maybe there's a problem with the robots...
罗伯森企图掩盖。。。
...and Robertson's covering it up.
无端猜疑？为什么？
Humoring you for no reason, why?
又是为什么！那些机器人能赚多少钱？
The same old why! How much money is there in robots?
我知道的只是一个老人有了麻烦
All I know is that old man was in trouble...
我自己不能独立完成 你是内部的人
...and I'm sick of doing this shit by myself. You're on the inside.
你要帮我发现这些机器人出了什么问题
You are going to help me find out what's wrong with these robots.
是你想他们有问题！
You want something to be wrong!
-这完全是报私仇！ -你想让我坐沙发？
-This is a personal vendetta! -You're putting me on the couch?
好吧，我坐下了
Okay, I'm on the couch.
一个出故障还不够 你想他们统统出故障
One defective machine's not enough. You need them all to be bad.
你才不关心兰尼的死 这完全是针对机器人的
You don't care about Lanning's death. This is about the robots...
还有不知道为什么你就是恨他们！ -让我们看看
-...and whatever reason you hate them! -Now let's see...
一个是拿枪对着我的脸 另一个是趁我还在里面的时候拆房子
...one of them put a gun in my face. Another tore a building down with me in it.
这里明明说了拆毁是设定在晚上八点的
It says demolition was scheduled for 8 p.m.
本来是早上八点，我才不管那东西是怎么说的
It was 8 a.m., and I don't give a shit what that thing says.
-你这完全是妄想狂 -你是。。。
-This is bordering on clinical paranoia. -You are the dumbest smart person...
-我这辈子见过的最蠢的聪明人 -好吧
-...I have ever met in my life! -Nice.
你凭什么觉得机器人那么完美？
What makes your robots so perfect?
是什么让他们比人类强那么多？
What makes them so much goddamn better than human beings?!
他们不是非理性的，或者有杀人倾向 的什么人！
They're not irrational, potentially homicidal maniacs, to start!
是啊，他们绝对的理性
That's true. They are definitely rational.
你是我见过的最蠢的蠢人！
You are the dumbest dumb person I've ever met!
或者。。。
Or...
只是因为他们是冷血的
...is it because they're cold...
没有感情的
...and emotionless...
他们什么也感觉不到 这是因为他们是安全的！
-...and they don't feel anything? -It's because they're safe!
是因为他们不会伤害你！
It's because they can't hurt you!
-一切都正常吗，女士？ -你想怎么样？
-ls everything all right, ma'am? -What do you want?
我探测到你的声音中的紧张压力在提升
I detected elevated stress patterns in your voice.
没事的
Everything's fine.
斯普那探员要离开了
Detective Spooner was just leaving.
你知道我们也没有那么不同
You know, we're not really that different from one another.
是吗？
Is that so?
一旦看到表象，我们就认为什么都知道了
One look at the skin and we figure we know just what's underneath.
你错了
And you're wrong.
问题在于，我是在意的
The problem is, I do care.
你处在危险中
You are in danger.
滚开！
Get the hell out of there.
未来就从今天开始，女士们先生们 从NS5开始
The future begins today, ladies and gentlemen, with the arrival of the NS-5.
更复杂，更智能，当然 三大定律，完全保护
More sophisticated, more intelligent and, of course, Three Laws safe.
有了每日更新，您的机器人永远不会和USR失去联系
With daily uplinks, your robot will never be out of communication with USR...
对于商业和家庭用途都是完美选择
...and will be the perfect companion for business or home.
用您旧型的NS4换新的NS5 未来将会更美好
Trade in your NS-4 for a bigger, better and brighter future.
但是要快，这个促销不会时间太长 USR出品
But hurry, this offer cannot last. A vailable from USR.
宝贝，你的脸怎么了？
Baby, what happened to your face?
又是那个弗兰克 墨菲打你了？
Did that boy, Frank Murphy, beat you up again?
琪琪，我从三年级开始就没见过弗兰克 墨菲了
Gigi, I haven't seen Frank Murphy since third grade.
哦，宝贝，他那时候打你可真厉害 我总是在想那时候
Oh, baby, he beat you so bad. I think about it all the time.
你一直做饼这么好吃 我想你可以去开店了
You keep making these pies this good, I may have to put you to work.
你喜欢那个饼是吗？
So you like the pie, huh?
你可以出来了
You can come in now.
你好，斯普那探员
Hello, Detective Spooner.
我赢了，德尔，我赢了那个抽奖
I won, Del! I won the lottery!
我们一直在做吃的
We been cooking like crazy.
你得把那个家伙赶出去，琪琪 那不安全
You gotta get rid of that thing, Gigi. It's not safe.
宝贝，你对他们偏见太多了 充满恐惧
Baby, you get too worked up about them. Too full of fear.
我看到那个好心的博士死的消息了
I saw in the news that nice doctor died.
兰尼博士是个好人 他把我的宝贝送回来了
Dr. Lanning was a good man. He gave me my baby back.
这就是为什么你这么不高兴的原因？
That why you've been so upset?
过去的就让他过去吧
You got to let the past be past.
哦，我怎么养了这么个小脏猫的？
Oh, how did I ever raise such a mess?
00:48:49,70